<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>toan&#39;s thoughts</title>
    <link>http://toanvuong.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on toan&#39;s thoughts</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://toanvuong.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>pintos part 1</title>
      <link>http://toanvuong.io/post/pintos-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://toanvuong.io/post/pintos-part-1/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-it&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While studying at Berkeley, I had friends who took our OS class. There, they used &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~kubitron/courses/cs162-F05/Nachos/walk/walk.html&#34;&gt;nachos&lt;/a&gt;, which was an operating system designed specifically for the OS class there. Originally written in C++, it has since been ported to Java and the official documentations do a great job explaining what it is. The OS class, along with the networking class, are among the few classes which I regret not having taken at Berkeley. If I recall however, they&amp;rsquo;ve since upgraded to using &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs162.eecs.berkeley.edu/info/&#34;&gt;pintos&lt;/a&gt; which was developed at &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.stanford.edu/class/cs140/projects/pintos/pintos_1.html&#34;&gt;Stanford&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen pintos merely through exposure: A friend of mine recently took the class at Stanford and recommends it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think as a developer, even if one doesn&amp;rsquo;t work directly at the OS level, knowledge &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; the OS is still absolutely essential in writing good code (In fact, I&amp;rsquo;d argue that this extends to the hardware level as well). I read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Design-UNIX-Operating-System/dp/0132017997&#34;&gt;The Design of the UNIX Operating System&lt;/a&gt; and loved it! In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about re-reading it one of these days. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of insights into how UNIX was designed, and by (partial) extension, Linux. You get to learn about how the filesystem works, pipes, file descriptors, and lots more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pintos&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pintos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not wanting to pollute my local machine, I chose to go the Docker route. Pretty simple. The contents of my Dockerfile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;FROM debian:jessie

RUN apt-get clean &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apt-get update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apt-get install --fix-missing -y nasm build-essential qemu gdb

env PATH /pintos/src/utils:$PATH
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This installs a couple of packages on top of the standard installation that&amp;rsquo;ll be used later. The PATH export will be explained below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, The Debian version is 8.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ /pintos/# cat /etc/debian_version
8.5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then grabbed a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;pintos.zip&#34;&gt;pintos.zip&lt;/a&gt; and unzipped it to my local machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build the Docker container, in the directory where we have our Dockerfile, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo docker build -t pintos .
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates a Docker image using the Dockerfile located in the current directory and names it &amp;ldquo;pintos.&amp;rdquo; After having built the Docker image as specified above (It might take a while, and for me, the &lt;code&gt;apt-get&lt;/code&gt; command occasionally fails with a TCP error so I have to re-run the command until it builds successfully), I run it with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo docker run -it -v ~/pintos:/pintos pintos /bin/bash
-it is for interactive mode
-v is to mount a local directory as a directory on the Docker host. Note that I unzipped the pintos source into ~/pintos
pintos is the name given to my Docker image
/bin/bash is the command to run on startup
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;now-we-re-talking&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re talking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;re in, there&amp;rsquo;s on last step to ensure things work properly. My workflow consists of editing things on my VM and &lt;em&gt;running&lt;/em&gt; things in my Docker image. There&amp;rsquo;s no reason why you can&amp;rsquo;t edit things in the Docker image (Though you&amp;rsquo;d need to ensure your favorite text editor is installed!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the file we&amp;rsquo;re interested in is under &lt;code&gt;pintos/src/utils/pintos-gdb&lt;/code&gt;. Open it up and modify the &lt;code&gt;GDBMACROS&lt;/code&gt; variable to:
&lt;code&gt;GDBMACROS=/pintos/src/misc/gdb-macros&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve followed everything thus far, &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt; should include the &lt;code&gt;/pintos/src/utils&lt;/code&gt; directory, which would allow for you to run the scripts there, including &lt;code&gt;pintos-gdb&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;pintos&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, within the Docker container, run &lt;code&gt;pintos-gdb&lt;/code&gt; and ensure that it does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; output:
&lt;code&gt;*** Pintos GDB macros will not be available ***&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full output should be similar to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pintos-gdb
GNU gdb (Debian 7.7.1+dfsg-5) 7.7.1
Copyright (C) 2014 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
License GPLv3+: GNU GPL version 3 or later &amp;lt;http://gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html&amp;gt;
This is free software: you are free to change and redistribute it.
There is NO WARRANTY, to the extent permitted by law.  Type &amp;quot;show copying&amp;quot;
and &amp;quot;show warranty&amp;quot; for details.
This GDB was configured as &amp;quot;x86_64-linux-gnu&amp;quot;.
Type &amp;quot;show configuration&amp;quot; for configuration details.
For bug reporting instructions, please see:
&amp;lt;http://www.gnu.org/software/gdb/bugs/&amp;gt;.
Find the GDB manual and other documentation resources online at:
&amp;lt;http://www.gnu.org/software/gdb/documentation/&amp;gt;.
For help, type &amp;quot;help&amp;quot;.
Type &amp;quot;apropos word&amp;quot; to search for commands related to &amp;quot;word&amp;quot;.
(gdb)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now quit &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt; by typing &lt;code&gt;q&lt;/code&gt; followed by &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we&amp;rsquo;ll also need to ensure pintos uses qemu by default instead of bochs. Both are OS emulators but qemu is the one we&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to use. Open up &lt;code&gt;/pintos/src/utils/pintos&lt;/code&gt; and look at line 103. It should be changed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    $sim = &amp;quot;qemu&amp;quot; if !defined $sim;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;running-your-first-pintos-application&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running your first pintos application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have everything setup, we can now build the threads module. Start by going into the threads directory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd /pintos/src/threads/
$ make # You can add a -j to run make in parallel
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re ready to run our first application:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd build
$ pintos run alarm-multiple
Use of literal control characters in variable names is deprecated at /pintos/src/utils/pintos line 915.
Prototype mismatch: sub main::SIGVTALRM () vs none at /pintos/src/utils/pintos line 939.
Constant subroutine SIGVTALRM redefined at /pintos/src/utils/pintos line 931.
qemu-system-i386 -device isa-debug-exit -hda /tmp/QUCaIlCx91.dsk -m 4 -net none -nographic -monitor null
PiLo hda1
Loading...........
Kernel command line: run alarm-multiple
Pintos booting with 3,968 kB RAM...
367 pages available in kernel pool.
367 pages available in user pool.
Calibrating timer...  602,112,000 loops/s.
Boot complete.
Executing &#39;alarm-multiple&#39;:
(alarm-multiple) begin
(alarm-multiple) Creating 5 threads to sleep 7 times each.
(alarm-multiple) Thread 0 sleeps 10 ticks each time,
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! It&amp;rsquo;s a very uneventful example but exciting nonetheless. Now we can follow the rest of the assignment from the official &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.stanford.edu/class/cs140/projects/pintos/pintos.html#SEC_Contents&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. See you at the finish line!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World!</title>
      <link>http://toanvuong.io/post/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://toanvuong.io/post/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to do this for a while but the planets have never aligned properly until today. This website will server as a dump for my thoughts which will mostly cover various software engineering related topics with occasional random thoughts in between. Whatever comes to my mind that I think is important to be recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hugo&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hugo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; is a static website generator. Given a pre-defined set of constraints and configurations and a set of inputs (In this case in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/toml-lang/toml&#34;&gt;toml&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&#34;&gt;markdown&lt;/a&gt; format), static website generators will generate a website for you, converting your inputs into static html files which can then be served using a webserver such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://httpd.apache.org/&#34;&gt;apache&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nginx.com/resources/wiki/&#34;&gt;nginx&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-hugo&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Hugo?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luck. In choosing Hugo, I started out by Googling for static website generators, which led me to a whole slew of them listed on a certain &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.staticgen.com/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. From there, I merely clicked on one semi-randomly. I didn&amp;rsquo;t care much about compilation speed since I didn&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;d have a whole lot of content that such a thing would matter. I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; care that it should be simple to use, as I didn&amp;rsquo;t want the tool to be in control and Hugo&amp;rsquo;s documentation advertises a new hugo site in 2 under minutes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, that number is fairly accurate. I grabbed the most recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spf13/hugo/releases/tag/v0.16&#34;&gt;release&lt;/a&gt;, installed the Debian package on my Ubuntu 16.04 VM:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;wget https://github.com/spf13/hugo/releases/download/v0.16/hugo_0.16-1_amd64.deb
sudo dpkg -i hugo_0.16-1_amd64.deb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instructions for other platforms can be found on Hugo&amp;rsquo;s website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing hugo gives us the hugo binary, and things are fairly straight forward from here so I won&amp;rsquo;t beat the deadhorse. This &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/overview/quickstart/&#34;&gt;quickstart&lt;/a&gt; guide should be all you need!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest annoyance I found was that my development environment wasn&amp;rsquo;t on localhost and thus a few special parameters to hugo was required. My full debug command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; hugo server --bind &amp;quot;192.168.1.121&amp;quot; --baseURL &amp;quot;http://192.168.1.121/&amp;quot; --buildDrafts --theme=hugo-steam-theme
# --bind Binds to a specific IP address
# --baseURL I assume determines the HTTP Host header that our hugo HTTP server accepts. By default this is localhost and will not work if the development environment isn&#39;t localhost, even if one sets the bind address differently
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I think hugo should be changed so that &lt;code&gt;--baseURL&lt;/code&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary. &lt;code&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to allow a single process to host multiple sites (virtual hosts) so there&amp;rsquo;s no point in requiring this parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;steam&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steam&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose &lt;a href=&#34;http://themes.gohugo.io/theme/steam/post/creating-a-new-theme/&#34;&gt;steam&lt;/a&gt; for its simplicity. Being new to Hugo, it took a little while to get everything running smoothly. The biggest thing here is to be sure to follow the theme&amp;rsquo;s installation instructions and look at the &lt;code&gt;hugo-steam-theme/exampleSite&lt;/code&gt; directory for usage examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another nice thing about steam is the ability to have custom pages with links. So this website can be used as a multi-purpose site rather than a blog-only page!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hosting&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hosting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a stranger to hosting services&amp;ndash;I have two VPSes, a Digital Ocean Droplet, and I&amp;rsquo;ve also used S3/Cloudfront at work. What I cared most about here was simplicity in hosting. I opted to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; for this task. Let me preface by saying that this isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary, and by default if you name your repo &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;github_handle&amp;gt;.github.io&lt;/code&gt; then the whole repo will be served out of the box without any issues. So by this point, &lt;a href=&#34;http://toad2186.github.io&#34;&gt;http://toad2186.github.io&lt;/a&gt; is already accessible. What I wanted was for &lt;a href=&#34;http://toanvuong.io&#34;&gt;http://toanvuong.io&lt;/a&gt; to be accessible and serving the same&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, in itself, wasn&amp;rsquo;t too difficult as I&amp;rsquo;m somewhat familiar with DNS. Basically you point the DNS for your domain to point to various Github servers. This can either be your apex domain (e.g. &lt;code&gt;toanvuong.io&lt;/code&gt;) or www (e.g. &lt;code&gt;www.toanvuong.io&lt;/code&gt;) domain. Github has a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/using-a-custom-domain-with-github-pages/&#34;&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; on how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that Github will serve your whole directory, and due to the way hugo works,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;hugo --theme=hugo-steam-theme
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;generates your website under the &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; directory. So you&amp;rsquo;ll end up having to go to &lt;code&gt;toanvuong.io/public/&lt;/code&gt;, and even then, this won&amp;rsquo;t work due to the way &lt;code&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt; generates links: namely, &lt;code&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt; generates &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coffeecup.com/help/articles/absolute-vs-relative-pathslinks/&#34;&gt;absolute&lt;/a&gt; links. This means that resources will be requested from &lt;code&gt;http://toanvuong.io/js/...&lt;/code&gt; for example, which is all wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get around this, I have two git repos. My main (source) repo is at &lt;code&gt;https://github.com/Toad2186/toad2186.github.io.src&lt;/code&gt; and I&amp;rsquo;ve created &lt;code&gt;https://github.com/Toad2186/toad2186.github.io&lt;/code&gt; just for the &lt;code&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; directory. Simple, but works. Shoot my a message if you&amp;rsquo;ve got a better idea! Quite frankly, I&amp;rsquo;m surprised Github doesn&amp;rsquo;t allow one to customize the root directory&amp;ndash;seems like it&amp;rsquo;d be a frequently requested feature given that static website generators would probably create these &amp;ldquo;build&amp;rdquo; directories as an output! Perhaps this has something to do with their integration with &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/using-jekyll-as-a-static-site-generator-with-github-pages/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. This brings me to my next point, we&amp;rsquo;d need to add a &lt;code&gt;.nojekyll&lt;/code&gt; (which can be an empty file) to the public folder so that github ignores its automatic jekyll build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last gripe with Github hosting is the lack of https which is sensible given the constraints. Unless they do some man-in-the-middle decryption/encryption or have an option for users to upload SSL certificates for their personal domains, it&amp;rsquo;s not possible for Github to provide HTTPS hosting. Furthermore, virtual hosts (which is what I assume Github uses) gets complicated with HTTPS since the HTTP Host header is no longer readable&amp;ndash;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-set-up-multiple-ssl-certificates-on-one-ip-with-apache-on-ubuntu-12-04&#34;&gt;TLS Server Name Indication extension&lt;/a&gt;is required for such a feat. So it&amp;rsquo;s possible, but difficult. For now though, since there isn&amp;rsquo;t any sensitive information flowing through these pages, http should be fine :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was rather simple and saved me the need to setup nginx on one of my existing virtual servers (or worse, spin up a new VPS!). Github it is, until I find a better host!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>http://toanvuong.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://toanvuong.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>contact</title>
      <link>http://toanvuong.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://toanvuong.io/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>